בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we today's דף daf is עין ו, Ayin
Vav, we're in the middle of עין ה עמוד ב, Ayin Hei
Amud Bet, we're dealing with, still in the middle of discussions around
the מן, man,
and we pick up where it says,
כתיב, ktiv, right, it is about ten lines down in the wide
lines right by the half-parentheses with the circle towards the beginning of
the line. כתיב: ktiv: ותעל שכבת הטל, v'ta'al shichvat hatal, and the
layer of טל tal rose up in the morning, וכתיב וברדת הטל
עליו, v'chtiv u'veredet hatal alav, and the layer of טל tal would
fall on the טל, tal, so, I'm sorry, and when and when
the טל tal would fall down, וברדת הטל, u'veredet hatal, excuse me,
when the טל tal would fall down, ירד המן עליו. yered haman
alav. So was the מן man on the טל tal or was
the טל tal on the מן? man? So אמר רב יוסף בר
חנינא: amar Rav Yosef bar Hanina: טל מלמעלה וטל מלמטה. tal milemala
vetal milmata. Yes, the dew was below and above and below. ודומה
כמי שמונח בקופסא. v'domeh k'mi shemunach b'kufsa. It was like you got
your bread in a package. The the מן man came packaged with
dew above and below. So it was very nicely, it isn't just
about the food, it's also how it's presented. דק, dak, דק מחספס,
dak mechuspas, like a
like a hoar frost is normally thin like hoar frost, thin, I
don't know, nobody knows, it's
hoar frost. אמר ריש לקיש: amar Reish Lakish: דבר
שנימוח על פיסות היד. davar shenimoach al pisot hayad. So they're also
trying to figure out what מחספס mechuspas means, so they read it
as a mnemonic: נימוח, nimoach, that's מחס, mechus, and פס pas on
the hands, so it's something that would dissolve on the hand.
It would melt in your hand and not in your mouth.
So, I don't know, yeah, well, but they melt, exactly. Good point.
So I don't know, did it mean that the the מן man
dissolved?
How do you how would you eat it? I don't know.
רבי יוחנן אמר: Rabbi Yochanan amar: דבר שנבלע במאתיים וארבעים ושמונה איברים.
davar shenivla b'matayim arbayim u'shmoneh eivarim. So something that gets absorbed into
your 248 limbs, meaning the the מן, man, you know, got well
well-digested and we're going to see even in a minute there was
no excrement that came from it, it was totally, you know, absorbed
by the body. Now the fact that he points out 248, you
know, why specifically mention the number, indicates a גימטריא, gematria, and מחספס
mechuspas if you look at it, right, the two ס samechs is
120, the פ peh is 80, that's 200, and the מ mem
and the ח het give you 48. The only problem is there's
an extra ו. vav. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ריש לקיש,
amar Reish Lakish, I'm sorry, so the גמרא Gemara says, מחספס טובא
הוי. mechuspas tuva havei. One minute, מחספס mechuspas is too much, it
doesn't come out to 248. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק: amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak: מחספס כתיב. mechuspas ktiv. It's written without the ו.
vav. Michael's going to go check, I didn't double check, whether it
actually is written without the ו vav or not. All right, so
now that I checked it, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, we taught. Now
we're going to continue with this idea.
לחם אבירים אכל איש. lechem abirim achal ish. There's a פרק perek
in תהלים Tehillim that is talking about the מן, man, and it
says the bread of strong of the strong ones, the food of
a man. The wonder bread. לחם שמלאכי השרת אוכלים אותו. lechem shemalachei
hashareit ochlim oto. דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. So what's אבירים,
abirim, the strong ones? It means the angels. That's what רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says.
וכשנאמרו דברים לפני רבי ישמעאל. u'keshenemru devarim lifnei Rabbi Yishmael. When they
told Rabbi Ishmael what Rabbi Akiva was saying, אמר להם, amar lahem,
he said to the students, צאו ואמרו לו לעקיבא, tzu v'imru lo
l'Akiva, go say to Akiva, עקיבא טעית, Akiva ta'ita, Akiva you made
a mistake. וכי מלאכי השרת אוכלים לחם? vechi malachei hashareit ochlim lechem?
Do the angels eat bread? והלא כבר נאמר לחם לא אכלתי ומים
לא שתיתי? vehalo kvar ne'emar lechem lo achalti umayim lo shatiti? Didn't
משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu didn't eat bread when he was up, and
certainly not up on הר סיני Har Sinai and certainly not the
angels. אלא מה אני מקיים אבירים? ela ma ani mekayem abirim? So
what does it mean, the strong ones? לחם שנבלע במאתיים וארבעים ושמונה
איברים. lechem shenivla b'matayim arbayim u'shmoneh eivarim. Just like we said before,
it gets absorbed into the 248 limbs. Now actually,
אבירים abirim is pretty close and איברים eivarim is pretty close to
248 right right there. It's 253, so I don't know, you're off
by five, I don't think you're allowed that in גימטריא, gematria, but
it's interesting that that even that is pretty close in the number.
Okay, so what does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva mean really?
Means angels? I don't know, I'm wondering if I haven't worked it
out but I'm wondering if this ties into the classic רבי ישמעאל
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Yishmael Rabbi Akiva, where you know רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael is דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם, dibra Torah kilshon bnai adam,
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva every single letter, you know, every single
קוצו של יוד kutzo shel yud is significant. So somehow he's trying
to bridge more heaven and earth, רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So the
eating of the מן man could be like eating of angel, I
don't know what it means eating of angel but trying to trying
to bridge more, you know, what God has given us to actual,
you know, to be that much closer, that much closer to the
heavenly experience.
There's a spiritual dimension to it already and then the angels you
know get their sustenance from.
Right, so so that's a good point too that it's just spiritually
sustaining and not just physically sustaining.
I
mean in a way the מלבי"ם Malbim explains this whole thing, you
know, on the המן haman itself as well. He says that, you
know, he has those two dimensions. There's לחם מן השמים, lechem min
hashamayim, right, so there's the physical aspect and then there's there's a
spiritual aspect. And then it says וילקטו המרבה והממעיט. vayilketu hamarbeh v'hamam'it.
then the
המרבה והממעיט hamarbe vehamamit is the spiritual dimension. For those that gained
a greater spiritual height, those that gained, but on the physical side
it was all the same for everybody. Okay. And he goes through
it.
Very nice. All right, I'm not sure I buy that as a
פשט, pshat, but it's a very nice point and I do think
you're right to say that that is part of what רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva is saying here is that there's a sense of spiritual
sustenance and I think that's a powerful metaphor, meaning as opposed to
what we were talking about before that like because of the מן
man you depend on God and therefore leads to a greater recognition
to think about it
in almost
more physical terms or more concrete terms as a sense of spiritual
sustenance. I think that's a very powerful point and I do think
that that ties into רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So thank you for
that.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אלא מה אני מקיים, ela ma
ani mekayem, if the מן man got absorbed and there was no
waste product of the מן, man, what do you do with the
fact that the תורה Torah seems to recognize that there was waste
product? ויתד תהיה לך על אזנך, veyated tihye lecha al azenecha, you
have to have for yourself a like a peg, something to dig,
a shovel to go and dig an outhouse when you leave the
camp and we have to defecate. So how do you where did
that come from? So דברים שתגרי אומות העולם מוכרין להם, devarim shetagrei
umot haolam mochrin lahem, that wasn't from the מן, man, that was
from stuff they bought from when they stopped in villages or whatever
in oases and they bought things from the from the non-Jews. Of
course why did they have to buy other food if they had
מן? man? Well we already learned before the מן man might have
tasted like anything but it didn't look like anything, it didn't feel
like anything and they still wanted other types of food. They wanted
nice bread. Right.
They complained about the מן. man.
Then they complained about the מן. man. It's the same thing day
after day. Exactly. Okay, רבי אלעזר בן פרטא Rabbi Elazar ben Prata
אומר, omer, אף דברים שתגרי אומות העולם מוכרין להם, af devarim shetagrei
umot haolam mochrin lahem, מן מפיגן. man mefigan. You know what? The
מן man was so magical that even the things that they bought
from the other nations, the מן man would sort of abate
their waste element and the מן man would be corrective and therefore
there would still be no waste that would come from those things.
אלא מה אני מקיים ויתד תהיה לך על אזנך? ela ma ani
mekayem veyated tihye lecha al azenecha? What does it mean to have
a shovel? לאחר שסרחו, leachar shesarchu,
after they sinned. Okay, meaning when they called it, רש״י Rashi says
לחם הקלוקל, lechem hakelokel, the cursed bread, you're calling it the cursed
bread, it's no longer going to have its magical properties.
They just said it was slush. All right.
I don't know, people just probably said the same thing. Anyway he's
making a point here which is that they had this so amazing,
magical מן man and because of they weren't satisfied and their complaint,
it changed and it became and it lost and it fell down
from its level. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar hakadosh baruch hu, אני
אמרתי, ani amarti, and if that point wasn't clear, God says I
thought you were כהמלאכי השרת, kehamalachei hasharet, interesting, right? Although this is
the רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael critique of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that
the angels don't eat bread, now we're re-evoking that image, I said
you would be like the angels and you had this מן man
that could be absorbed into your limbs, עכשיו אני מטריח אותם שלוש
פרסאות, achshav ani matriach otam shalosh parsaot, now the מן man is
going to lead to waste products, you're going to have to defecate
and you're going to have to walk
three פרסאות, parsaot, which is twelve מיל, mil, like twelve kilometers. You'll
have to leave the camp in order to go to the bathroom.
דכתיב, dechtiv, we'll see ויחנו על הירדן מבית הישימות עד אבל השטים,
vayachanu al hayarden mibeit hayeshimot ad avel hashittim, they camp by the
Jordan from בית הישימות Beit HaYeshimot to שטים. Shittim. ואמר רבה בר
בר חנה, veamar Rabbah bar bar Chana, לדידי חזי לי ההוא אתרא,
ledidi chazi li hahu atra, I saw that place בית הישימות Beit
HaYeshimot and אבל השטים Avel HaShittim והוה תלתא פרסא, vehavah tlata parsa,
and it was three פרסאות. parsaot. So we see that the camp
was three פרסאות parsaot long and if you had to leave the
camp to go to the bathroom and you're at one end of
the camp, now why couldn't you go to the closest side? Meaning
from any point in the camp it should only be one and
a half פרסאות. parsaot. So גמרא Gemara says no, ותנא, vetana, we
learned in a ברייתא, braita, כשהן נפנין, keshen nifnin, when they had
to go and relieve themselves, אין נפנין לא לפניהם ולא לצדיהם, ein
nifnin lo lifneihem velo litzdeihem, they couldn't go front or the sides
of
the camp because the ענן anan might go in that direction and
then they'd be going over the outhouses. אלא לאחוריהם, ela leachoreihem, they
had to go to the back of the camp, the place they
came from, because the one thing they knew somehow was that they
would not be directly retracing their steps. So if you had to
go to the back of the camp outside the camp from the
back exit and you were way in the front, you might have
to travel a whole three פרסאות. parsaot.
I'll tell you, all the miracles we've learned, I buy every single
one of those fine. This? Not buying it. No way they're gonna
make a person walk such a distance. Not a chance.
All right. ועתה נפשנו יבשה, veata nafshenu yevesha, now we're going back
to them complaining. Now our soul is dried up, אין כל, ein
kol, there's nothing, בלתי אל המן עינינו, bilti el haman eineinu, all
we got is מן. man. There's such a great רש״י Rashi on
that פסוק. pasuk. מן בשחרית מן בערבית מן היום מן אמש מן
דאתמול, man bashacharit man baarbit man hayom man emesh man de-etmol, right?
מן man in the morning, מן man in the evening, מן man
today, מן man yesterday, מן man the day before. So אין כל,
ein kol, so anyway, עסי מן זה, assi man ze, so what
was their complaint? Their complaint was עסי מן זה שתפח במעיהם, assi
man ze shetipach bimeihem, so they couldn't accept the miraculous aspects of
the מן. man. They said it's going in the end blow up.
We're eating and eating and eating and we're not defecating. Something's going
to happen to us. כלום יש ילוד אשה שמכניס ואינו מוציא, klum
yesh yelud isha shemachnis veeino motzi, is there anybody who's a child
of a woman meaning is there any human being who can eat
without having to go to the bathroom? So therefore, maybe that's... Sense
of like dried up, it's shriveling us up inside. Anyway, they were,
so they reacted, it wasn't just they complained, they couldn't even accept
its miraculous quality. וכשנאמרו דברים לפני רבי ישמעאל. Ucheshene'emru devarim lifnei Rabbi
Yishmael.
Now, when the words were said to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, it's
funny because before we said נאמרו דברים לפני רבי ישמעאל, ne'emru devarim
lifnei Rabbi Yishmael, so אמר להם, amar lahem, so it seems a
little bizarre, seems like we're repeating, yeah, I don't know, it's not
clear, it seems like we're repeating what we said before. אמר להם
אל תקרי אבירים אלא איברים דבר שנבלע במאתים וארבעים ושמונה איברים. Amar
lahem al tikri abirim ela evarim davar shenivla bematayim ve'arba'im ushmonah evarim.
אלמאי מתקיים יתה ותקע ידיו אלו ואלו דברים שבאים להם, Almai mitkayem
yete vetaka yadav elu ve'elu devarim sheba'im lahem, this is another version,
basically it's repeating his response, but now going back what does it
mean that they had to go to the bathroom? So before we
said אומות העולם, umot ha'olam, now we're saying ודברים שבאים להם ממדינת
הים, udevarim sheba'im lahem mimedinat hayam, things that came from overseas, which
is bizarre. Overseas? I don't get it.
Maybe they didn't get blueberries from Italy.
Right. דבר אחר. Davar acher. אומות העולם. Umot ha'olam. Okay. Anyway, anyway,
fine. That's one explanation, a type of a spiritual existence, even according
to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, and then they couldn't accept being at
that level, or they just סתם stam complained and they were never
satisfied and then they fell down from that level. דבר אחר לחם
אבירים אכל איש זה
יהושע.
Davar acher Lechem abirim achal
ish zeh Yehoshua. So איש ish is יהושע, Yehoshua, שיורד לו, sheyorad
lo, top of ע"ו עמוד א', Ayin Vav Amud Aleph, שיורד לו
מן כנגד כל ישראל. sheyorad lo man kineged kol Yisrael. He had
an equal amount of מן man equal to the entire Jewish people.
Everybody, well thank you Michael. Anyway, כתיב הכא איש, ksiv hacha ish,
it says here איש, ish, וכתיב התם קח לך את יהושע בן
נון איש אשר רוח בו. uchsiv hatam kach lecha et Yehoshua bin
Nun ish asher ruach bo. So רש"י Rashi says everybody, רש"י Rashi
translates this very literally and it means that everybody got one עומר
omer and in front of יהושע's Yehoshua door and what he brought
into his house was you know two million עומרים. omers. I don't
exactly know how he fit it all in and what he did
with all of it, but that's what he says he got an
equivalent amount. Now obviously it's supposed to be indicating that you know
like the leader is כנגד כל הדור kineged kol hador and on
him is the responsibility and he represents the entire generation. It seems
to be the point here, although interesting focusing on יהושע Yehoshua who
is yet to take the mantle of leadership. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא משה, ve'eima Moshe, how about משה?
Moshe? That would at least make more sense. דכתיב והאיש משה עניו
מאד, dichsiv veha'ish Moshe anav me'od, so איש משה. ish Moshe. דנין
איש מאיש ואין דנין איש מזה האיש. Danin ish me'ish ve'ein danin
ish mizeh ha'ish. Okay, it's not the exact same word. Fine.
שאלו תלמידיו את רבי שמעון בן יוחאי. Sha'alu talmidav et Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai. So again I don't know exactly what to do with
that point about יהושע. Yehoshua. The students asked רבי שמעון בן יוחאי.
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. Where am I? את רבי שמעון בן יוחאי
מפני מה לא ירד
להם לישראל מן פעם אחת בשנה? Et Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai mipnei
mah lo yarad lahem leYisrael man pa'am achat beshanah? Why did they
have to go out every single day? Wouldn't it have been a
lot easier once a year and then you take it in and
you store it up? Of course that's the point of the פסוק,
pasuk, but okay, which is you know that every day you depend
on God. Let's see what his answer is. אמר להם אמשול לכם
משל, Amar lahem emshol lachem mashal, let me give you an analogy.
למה הדבר דומה? Lemah hadavar domeh? What's it similar to? למלך בשר
ודם שיש לו בן אחד. Lemeilech basar vadam sheyesh lo ben echad.
A king has one son, פסק לו מזונותיו פעם אחת בשנה. pasak
lo mezonotav pa'am achat beshanah. If he writes him out a check
for all of the food for the year, deposits money in a
bank account for him to pay for him for the year, right,
so what happens, you know, pays the college, the food, you know,
puts him on the meal plan for the year. So פעם אחת
בשנה ולא היה מקביל פני אביו אלא פעם אחת בשנה. pa'am achat
beshanah velo hayah makbil pnei aviv ela pa'am achat beshanah.
He'd only call home and write home once a year when he
needed him to pay next year's tuition and pay the next year's
food
bill. So פסק מזונותיו בכל יום. pasak mezonotav bechol yom. If every
day he had to give him a daily allowance for him to
go ahead and get his food, והיה מקביל פני אביו בכל יום
ויום. vehayah makbil pnei aviv bechol yom vayom. So every day he
would have to come home and he would have to greet his
father and show respect to his father in order to get the
next day's allowance. אף ישראל מי שיש לו ארבעה וחמישה בנים. Af
Yisrael mi sheyesh lo arba'ah vachamishah banim. So by the Jewish people,
somebody had four five children,
היה דואג ואומר, hayah do'eg ve'omer, he would be anxious and he
would say, שמא לא ירד מן למחר, shema lo yered man lemachar,
maybe the מן man won't come tomorrow, ונמצאו כולם מתים ברעב, venimtzu
kulam metim bera'av, and every day and any day they would die
in hunger, נמצאו כולם מכוונים את לבם לאביהם שבשמים. nimtzu kulam mechavnim
et libam la'avihem shebashamayim. So every day they would know they depended
on God and every day they'd have to be focused on their
connection to God and their worship of God and their proper behavior
because they had that sense of uncertainty. And therefore that's what that's
the importance of the מן, man, which is really פשט pshat of
the פסוקים, psukim, right? You know the פסוקים psukim say ויענך וירעיבך
ויאכילך את המן, vaya'ancha vayar'ivacha vayachilcha et haman, you know the המן,
haman, ענותך ולנסותך. anotcha ulenasotcha. What is it? But the פסוק pasuk
says
כי לא על הלחם לבדו יחיה
האדם כי על כל
מוצא פי ה' יחיה האדם.
Ki lo al
halechem
levado yichyeh ha'adam ki al kol motza pi Hashem yichyeh ha'adam. Right,
so that dependency on God you know seems to be a very
major part of the theme you know. וילקטו דבר יום ביומו למען
אנסנו הילך בתורתי אם לא. veyilketu devar yom beyomo lema'an anassenu hayelech
betorati im lo. Now the other interesting thing though here that the
גמרא Gemara is a little bit you know I don't know because
one of the things that you could you know the גמרא Gemara
did a subtle shift because it is true that I think the
simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is that sense of daily dependency,
but I think a major theme of the פסוק pasuk is to
develop a sense of faith and trust. Meaning it leads to a
point where you have faith in God and you trust that God
will bring down the מן mon on a daily basis which seems
to be the point of שבת, Shabbat, of ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat,
right? The people that go out and they gather on שבת, Shabbat,
the problem is not just that they're violating שבת. Shabbat. The problem
is is that you have to have faith that you will that
you know that you'll that it'll be okay that there won't be
מן mon on שבת Shabbat and it will still be okay, right?
And the same is you have to have faith not to collect
extra and have that faith that God will bring it, you know,
you want to store up, I mean that idea of not storing
up is exactly what's going on here. But I think you can
just frame it in two ways. One idea is getting you to
a place where you have the faith in God and you have
that you're sort of sort of and you're not anxious on a
day to day basis. You actually are good on a day to
day basis because you develop that sense of trust and faith. The
other sense here is that no every day you will be anxious
because you won't have that that confidence but that will lead you
to be more to be more you know attentive to how you
act and to focus more on your worship of God. So they're
related but I think there's a significant difference you know what type
of sort of religious mentality are we working for? Are we working
to keep somebody nervous and the more I can keep you nervous
and concerned the more you're going to be in line or are
we working for a sense of developed a sense of you know
of of confidence and faith in God and that's like and that's
the relationship that we're looking for? So I think there's an interesting
shift here from what I would have thought would have been the
emphasis of the פסוקים. Pesukim.
Just think of the details of it. Let's say you have four
or five children. You know there's no food. One person...
Right although you know I I don't know about that there's no
like I have so many mouths to feed. Like if it was
just me I'll skip by for a day or two you know?
But yeah so that's the assumption I mean because
they davened for cactus or something?
Right right. What was the alternative? Yeah yeah I don't know. So
it is interesting the way the גמרא Gemara is framing it you
know? But clearly that sense of that you don't know that you're
going to get מן mon the next day or you don't have
something to be confident about you know is clearly what's going on
in the פסוקים. Pesukim. Okay.
דבר אחר שהיו אוכלין אותו כשהוא חם. Davar acher she-hayu ochlin oto
k'she-hu cham. Now this is a fascinating talk about that being a
subtle shift from the פסוק. Pasuk. Here's a more radical shift from
the פסוק. Pasuk. You know why it came down on a daily
basis? Because it should be fresh baked bread that shouldn't be stale.
Now of course there could have been a miracle it could have
been fresh it could have tasted fresh you know even six months
later but again that goes to the experiential reality that sense of
bread delivered in the morning freshly baked bread. So now we're back
to it just being such an amazing experience taking away from that
focus on what it meant in terms of the religious mindset.
דבר אחר Davar acher that's true.
דבר אחר מפני משא הדרך. Davar acher mipnei masah ha-derech.
They wouldn't have to שלעפ shlep 20 pounds of bread with them
throughout the year. So the next explanation is like why did we
what good was the דבר אחר? Davar acher? We liked the first
explanation better. I mean this is just saying yeah look how wondrous
it was. But it doesn't get to the spiritual message which seems
to be the point. Okay. וכבר היה רבי טרפון ורבי ישמעאל וזקנים
יושבין ועוסקים בפרשת המן. u-khvar hayah Rabbi Tarfon v'Rabbi Yishmael u-zekenim yoshvin
v'oskim b'Parashat Ha-Mon.
Fascinating. Sometimes you have like this idea כבר היו kevar hayu you
know they were הולכים בדרך holchim ba-derech and they were talking about
something. Here they were sitting down and they were talking about מן,
mon, פרשת המן. Parashat Ha-Mon. והיה רבי אלעזר המודעי יושב ביניהם ve-hayah
Rabbi Elazar Ha-Modai yoshev beinehem and Rabbi Elazar Ha-Modai was among them.
נענה רבי אלעזר המודעי ואמר. na'anah Rabbi Elazar Ha-Modai ve-amar. Rabbi Elazar
Ha-Modai spoke up and said: מן שירד לישראל היה גבוה שישים אמה.
mon she-yarad le-Yisrael hayah gavo'ah shishim amah. Again we're back to like
wonder stories like some you know pearls would come down with it
diamonds. Now we're saying it was 60 אמה amah tall. It fell
down so much that it was like you know 90 100 feet
tall. אמר לו רבי טרפון: amar lo Rabbi Tarfon: מודעי עד מתי
אתה מגבב דברים ומביא עלינו? Modai ad matai atah megavev devarim u-mevi
aleinu? How long are you going to be sort of piling up
things, again piling up the מן, mon, piling up words and bringing
it to us? So meaning where the heck did you get this
idea from? אמר לו amar lo so he said back: רבי מקרא
אני דורש. Rabbi mikra ani doresh. I get it from
a פסוק. Pasuk. חמש עשרה אמה מלמעלה גברו המים. chamesh esreh amah
mi-lemala gavru ha-mayim. By the flood it says fifteen אמות amot above
the waters you know were powerful you know were mighty ויכסו ההרים
va-yekhasu he-harim and they covered the mountains. So which fifteen אמות amot
measured from where? וכי חמש עשרה אמה בעמק? ve-khi chamesh esreh amah
ba-emek? Is it fifteen אמות amot high you know off of the
valley floor? Or is it חמש עשרה בשפלה chamesh esreh ba-shfelah or
from the lowlands? Or חמש עשרה בהרים chamesh esreh ba-harim is it
fifteen אמות amot you know off of the mountains? Fifteen אמות amot
higher than what? What was your level? וכי מים שווין שווין קיימין?
ve-khi mayim shavin shavin kayamin? Let's say you say it was all
fifteen אמות amot higher than the valley you know off the valley
floor and fifteen אמות amot off the mountain floor. What is it
going to be like? Falling in layers like you know wherever you
go it's fifteen אמות amot higher than wherever your ground level is?
ועוד תיבה היכי סגיא? ve-od tevah heichi sagya? How would the boat
float if the water were different heights in different places? אלא נבקעו
כל מעינות תהום רבה. ela nivke'u kol ma'aynot tehom rabah. All of
the you know all of the wellsprings of the great depth opened
up quoting the פסוק Pasuk עד דאשוו מיא בהדי טורי ad d'ashvu
maya bahadi turei until first of all the first thing was that
the water level was topped leveled off to the top of all
the mountains. והדר *Vehadar*, once it reached the top of the mountains,
חמש עשרה אמה מלעילא גברו המים *chamisha asar ama mileila gavru hamayim*,
then another fifteen אמות amos *amos* higher than the top of the
mountains. Okay, now why we're saying that is not clear because at
the end of the day we're only going to focus on the
fifteen אמות *amos*, so this really seems like a digression about where
it was fifteen אמות *amos* measured from. Because if you think about
it, the point he's making now is it was a lot more
than fifteen אמות *amos* of water, right? It was the height of
mountains plus fifteen אמות *amos*. You know, so it could be a
thousand אמות *amos*, but in the end we're dropping all of that
and we're just focusing on the fifteen.
Maybe, maybe, maybe. וכי איזה מידה מרובה מידה טובה או מידה פורענות
*Vechi eizo mida meruba, mida tova o mida puranyuot*? Which way, what
you know what's greater? God's kindness, God's the when He pays back
good deeds or when he or when he does or when he
punishes? הוי אומר מידה טובה ממידת פורענות *Hevi omer mida tova mimida
puranyut*. We know the good, you know the rewarding. Why do we
know it? רש״י *Rashi* quotes the same מדרש *midrash* because it says
when it says that God is, you know, keeping the sin, He
says, you know, פוקד עון אבות על בנים ועל בני בנים על
שלשים ועל רבעים *poked avon avot al banim ve'al benei banim al
shileshim ve'al rive'im*, four generations. But when it says God remembers the
good, He says, He says, you know, נוצר חסד לאלפים *notzer chesed
la'alafim*,
right, to two thousand generations. So you see how much greater the
good, paying back the good is than paying back punishment. הוי אומר
*Hevi omer*, so במידת פורענות הוא אומר *bemida puranyut hu omer*, now
what does it say by the punishment? וארובות השמים נפתחו *va'arubot hashamayim
niftachu*. The, the, what do you call it, the skylights, the windows
of heavens opened up. במידה טובה הוא אומר *bemida tova hu omer*,
and by the מן man *man*, what does it say? ויצו שחקים
ממעל *vayitzav shechakim mima'al*, God commanded the heavens above, ודלתי שמים פתח
ve-daltei shamayim patach *vedaltei shamayim patach*, and the doors of the heaven
opened. So by the way, it is, you know, interesting seeing that
parallel image: opening the windows to pour down the rain, opening the
doors to pour down the מן man. *man*. וימטר עליהם מן man
לאכול *vayamter aleihem man leechol*, and here's even the verb of rain.
He caused the מן man. *man* to rain down upon them to
eat. ודגן שמים נתן למו *vedagan shamayim natan lamo*, and He gave
them the, the grain of heavens. So now we have a comparison
of door to window. כמה ארובות יש בדלת *kama arubot yesh badelet*?
How many windows, like panes, can you have in a door? I
suppose that, you know, you could have like a door divided into
quarters, you know, and you have little, like, you know, windows in
the doors. So how many doors do you have per window per
door? ארבע *arba*, four. ארבע הרי כאן שמונה *arba harei kan shemoneh*.
So, so four times two doors is eight. So it was ארובות
השמים נפתחו arubot ha-shamayim niftachu *arubot hashamayim niftachu*, but then there were
two doors which are eight. So but of course there were two
ארובות *arubot*, ארובות השמים *arubot hashamayim*, so it's two windows were opened,
but two doors, so two doors is eight, is eight windows, so
it's four times as much. ונמצא מן man לישראל גבוה ששים אמה
*venimtza man lishrael gavo'a shishim ama*, so four times fifteen. If there
was fifteen אמות *amot* of rain, there were sixty אמות *amot* of
מן man. *man*. All right, so that was a very complicated thing
and again why it had to be fifteen אמות *amos* above the
mountains I don't know. תניא *Tanya*, איסי בן יהודה אומר *Isi ben
Yehuda omer*, מן man שירד לישראל היה מתגבר ועולה עד שראו אותו
כל מלכי מזרח ומערב *man sheyarad lishrael haya mitgaber ve'oleh ad she'ro'u
oto kol malchei mizrach uma'arav*. So, so at least this is not
just a number, this is a more visual image. It went so
high that all of the kings of the East and the West
could see it, meaning so it was visible around the world. שנאמר
Shenemar: *shene'emar*, תערוך לפני שלחן נגד צוררי *ta'aroch lefanai shulchan neged tzorerai*.
God, You have laid for me a table opposite my enemies, says
דוד *David*. So that means my enemies, the opposing kings, those are
דוד'ס *David's*, you know, sort of nemesis, the ones at דוד'ס *David's*
level, you know, he so would be other kings and they see
that God has laid the table. It's נגד *neged*, it's in front
of them. So what table does God lay? God laid the table
of מן man *man* and everybody else could see it. וכוסי רויה
*vekosi revaya*. So אמר אביי *amar Abaye*, שמע מינה *shema mina*, כוסו
דדוד לעלמא דאתי מחזיק מאתן ועשרין וחד לוגא *koso deDavid le'alma de'ati
machazik matan ve'esrin vechad luga*. So since it says my cup is
overflowing, so or sated, so what does that mean? So he's saying
the cup of דוד המלך *David HaMelech* for in the world to
come—notice how we jumped back of this פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*, on the
one hand it was talking about the מן man *man* in the
time of the מדבר *midbar*, now we're talking about, you know, לעתיד
לבוא *le'atid lavo*. So this whole תערוך לפני *ta'aroch lefanai* is it
a future vision? Is it a past vision? Anyway so the cup
of דוד המלך *David HaMelech* will be two hundred and twenty-one לוג
*log*. שנאמר Shenemar, כוסי רויה *shene'emar kosi revaya*, ורויה בגימטריא הכי הוי
*verevaya begimatria hachi avei*. We're back to גימטריא *gematria*. So רויה *revaya*,
ריש *resh* is two hundred, ו vav. *vav* and ה Hashem
*hei* is eleven, י *yud* is another ten, two hundred and twenty-one
לוג *log*. So okay. Anyway so you see that there are others
that say the idea that the מן *man* was so high. הכי
הכי *Hachi hachi*, so מה ששנו *mah sheshno*? לא *lo*, לא דמיא
*lo damya*, it's not similar. התם בארבעים יומין *hatam bearbaim yomin*. There
by the rain, jumping over this whole תערוך לפני שלחן *ta'aroch lefanai
shulchan*, there by the rain, by the flood, it rained for forty
days. הכא בחד שעתא *hacha bacha sha'ata*, here it only the מן
*man* only came down in one moment. So even if it was
coming down at a greater pace, you know it takes time for
the snow to accumulate, it takes time for the מן *man* to
accumulate. So it might have fallen down at a quicker pace but
it was not over forty days, so it did not get that
high. התם לכולי עלמא *hatam lechulei alma*, not only that, there it
was It was for the whole world it rained. הכא לישראל לחודיה,
here it was just for the Jewish people. So maybe it was
not the same, you know, enormity of it. ונפישי שלוחיה טפי Ve-nefishi
shluchei tufei and there also would be a lot left over, you
know, what do you need all that מן for? Okay, so the
Gemara says, רבי אליעזר המודעי פתיחה פתיחה גמר. Rabbi Eliezer ha-Moda'i peticha
peticha gamar. Yes, you could make those distinctions, but nevertheless, Rabbi Eliezer
ha-Moda'i says in one place it says ויפתח, vayiftach, ארובות השמים נפתחו
and it says ודלתי שמים פתח and he wants to learn that
they were equal and therefore he wants to learn that there were
sixty אמות worth of מן.
Okay, so we have like a מן camp, a weather forecast every
day.
Yeah, right, exactly.
Cloudy with eight inches
predicted to go up to ten inches. That reminds me of Steve
Martin in L.A. Story. Did you see that movie? So he's like
the weather man for L.A. So every day for L.A. it's like
seventy-two degrees. So he says seventy-two degrees, seventy-two degrees, seventy-two degrees, the
whole week seventy-two degrees. It's like מן.
What? Hasn't an issue once where the weather men were part of
a larger union and they went on strike, but they went on
strike, so you knew every day it was going to be seventy-two.
So right, every day you could predict מן and you'd be right.
Okay, anyway. All right, so that was a whole nice long discussion
about the מן. Again, what I do find interesting because I tried,
you know, to tease out and here and there the Gemara would
be explicit about some of the religious points, you know, particularly that
sense of dependence on God, the point that we just made. But
you know, there's other discussions where they're just basically like wonder stories
about how amazing the מן is, you know, and there's some places
where the Gemara, you know, seems to be even talking about, you
know, there's almost a sense of like getting into the physical experience
as well. You had Rabbi Akiva who said, you know, it was
miraculous food, spiritual sustenance. Anyway, it's interesting because it's not all an
explicit message about how to make your eating religious. Right? There's elements
of that, but that's not all that it is. And it's again,
I just think it's fascinating in its position here in יומא, Yoma,
which is about how fasting is obviously a religious experience. It's not
as much of a parallel as I'm saying as I would have
hoped for. You know, there's a lot of discussion of eating, but
it's not all clear how to frame it all as saying, you
know, how we're going to make eating also be a religious experience.
There are elements of it, but a lot of it is other
things as well. All right, and now we return to the הלכה
halacha aspects of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Let's take a look and
of fasting. So what?
I think that it was very spiritual.
It was, but I'm just saying not all parts of that discussion,
right?
It's about all the things that go into what makes a person
feel satiated inside, all the aesthetic and all those other dimensions.
Yes, that I think was a very, you know, a repeating theme
which was very powerful, right? It's not just the way it tastes,
it's the way it looks, it's the way its texture, it's the
way it's presented, it's its appearance, right? All of those things, yes,
were very much did talk to the reality of the, you know,
eating experience and the power and you should eat with, you know,
in the light and not in the dark. So you know, it
did talk about the experience of eating, that it did. But exactly
framing, okay, that's all very interesting, what does that say about eating
as a religious experience? You know, that requires a lot more connecting
of dots than the Gemara, I mean, in one or two places
it did, but it did not do it in all those places.
You know, and even if you think about the story, oh, well,
with the מן would come perfume, with the מן would come pearls
and diamonds. In other words, parts of it were just like wonder
stories, which was like, okay, and what's other than saying how amazing
it was and how we'not at that מדרגה, madrega, you know, what's
sort of the point of that? I mean, the point is to
say, look at how amazing it was when you were connected to
God and you had all of this, you know, directly provided for
you. All right. הני חמשה עינויים כנגד מי? Hani chamisha inuyim keneged
mi? So now, what can you not do on יום כיפור? Yom
Kippur? You can't eat or drink, that's two. You also can't what?
Anoint yourself, bathe, sex, and shoes. So that's four more. So it's
interesting though, the Gemara starts by calling it five. Okay, so it
knows that there's a number five that it's going to get to.
Where do you get these five עינויים? inuyim? So אמר רב חסדא
כנגד חמשה עינויים שבתורה. Amar Rav Chisda keneged chamisha inuyim she-baTorah. It
says five times you should תענו, te'anu, you should afflict yourselves. בעשור,
אך בעשור, שבת שבתון, ושבת שבתון, ועשה לכם. Be-asor, ach be-asor, Shabbat
shabbaton, ve-Shabbat shabbaton, ve-asah lachem. So
basically the various places in פנחס Pinchas and אמור Emor and in
אחרי מות Acharei Mot where it speaks about יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
if you go and count it up, you will see that it
mentions five times you should afflict yourself. Actually תוספות Tosafot points out
ironically, well, I'll just do another line. So the Gemara says הני
חמשה הוו ואנן שית תנן. Hani chamisha hava ve-anan shis tnan. What
do you mean? The משנה Mishna says six, eating and drinking plus
four more. So again, it's pretty funny. We said where do we
know, you know, we start with five, we quote five, and we
have six. Now, תוספות Tosafot actually points out that there actually is
a sixth פסוק. pasuk: It says כי כל הנפש אשר לא תעונה.
Ki kol ha-nefesh asher lo te'uneh. Okay, but that is, that mentions
afflicting, but it says what if you don't do it, here's your
punishment, but only five times does it command that you should ועניתם,
ve-initem, that you should afflict. So five times it commands afflicting and
the Gemara says but our משנה Mishna says six.
Okay, so now.
No, food and eating and drinking counts as one. Drinking is like
eating, meaning it's more like consumption, various forms of consumption, and not
totally because you remember the משנה Mishnah says that eating and drinking
don't combine, they have different quantities, and if you eat and drink,
you know,
if you eat the quantity minus epsilon and drink the quantity minus
epsilon, you still haven't transgressed. They don't combine. Nevertheless, in this counting
of five versus six, we count them as one thing, as consumption.
דאמר ריש לקיש, De-amar Reish Lakish, מנין לשתייה שהיא בכלל אכילה? minayyin
l'shtiyah shehi bichlal achilah? How do you know drinking is included in
the concept of eating, of consuming? שנאמר: ואכלת לפני ה' אלהיך מעשר
דגנך תירשך ויצהרך, Ve-achalta lifnei Hashem Elokecha ma'asar deganecha tiroshcha ve-yitzharecha, you
should eat
before ה' your God the מעשר Ma'aser of your grain, of your
wine, and of your oil. Okay, so תירש, Tirosh, now oil you
could say is an eating because you dip stuff in oil. But
wine, תירש חמרא הוא, Tirosh chamra hu, תירש Tirosh is wine, וקרי
ליה ואכלת, ve-karei lei ve-achalta, and it says eat it. So you
see you can use the word eat to refer to drinking.
ממאי? Mi mai? How do you know that? ודילמא דאכלי ליה על
ידי אניגרון? Ve-dilma de-achlei al yedei anigron? Maybe they ate the wine
through אניגרון, anigron, which is some type of a food that was
steeped in wine, like some type of boiled vegetables that were steeped
with wine, so you're it's part of a food, it's a sauce
of a food and it's an act of eating. דאמר רבה בר
שמואל, De-amar Rabbah bar Shmuel, אניגרון מיא דסילקא, anigron maya de-silka, אניגרון
anigron is the water of beets, of boiled beets with wine mixed
in or something. אחסידרון מיא דכולהי שלקי, Achsidron maya de-chulei shalki, and
an אחסידרון achsidron is some type of a water of other cooked
vegetables. So maybe it's some wine in a as a as a
sauce, as some type of a dish. אלא אמר רב אחא בר
יעקב מהכא, Ela amar Rav Ach bar Yaakov me-hacha, from the following
פסוק: pasuk ונתתה הכסף בכל אשר תאוה נפשך, Ve-natata hakesef bechol asher
te'aveh nafshecha,
this is the money of מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, you should apply
the money with all that your soul desires, ובבקר ובצאן וביין ובשכר,
uvabakar uvatzoan uvayayin uvashichar,
you know, cattle and sheep and wine and mead, שכר שתיה הוא.
shichar shtiyah hu.
So wine you've already got around, you say wine could be a
type of dip. But שכר, shichar, but that's a drink, you know,
it's beer, it's mead. וכתב רחמנא ואכלת, U-cheiv Rachmana ve-achalta, and it
says the end of the פסוק pasuk. is, ואכלת לפני ה' אלהיך,
ve-achalta lifnei Hashem Elokecha,
I think is the end of the פסוק. pasuk So anyway, all
of these things it ends by saying and you shall eat. So
eating is and it's applying that verb to שכר. shichar. So the
גמרא Gemara says ממאי? mi mai? How do you know that? ודילמא
הכא נמי דאכלי על ידי אניגרון? Ve-dilma hacha nami de-achlei al yedei
anigron? Maybe here too whatever it was, the beer, the mead, you
put it in some type of a sauce and it was some
type of a dish. No, שכר כתיב. shichar ketiv. If it uses
the word שכר, shichar, it means מידי דמשכר, midi de-meshakker, means that
it has the power to intoxicate. And you don't get drunk by
eating some type of things that has a little alcohol mixed up.
I mean, of course, it does, you know, it shouldn't really matter
if you drink if you eat enough of it, you know, depending
on how much alcohol is in your food. But the גמרא Gemara
understands that drunk is something that you're going to be imbibing and,
you know, drinking in serious quantities. That's going to lead to you
getting drunk. So if it says שכר, shichar, it must mean in
its liquid form. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ודילמא דבילה
קעילית? ve-dilma dvela kelit?
Maybe it is a type of a these pressed dates of קעילית
Keilit that somehow had the power to intoxicate. דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא: Baraita: אכל דבילה קעילית ושתה דבש וחלב,
Achal dvela kelit ve-shasa dvash v'chalav, if you ate this these dates
of קעילית Keilit
or
you drank honey and milk, ונכנס למקדש, ve-nichnas lamikdash, חייב chayav or
some say לוקה, loket, you transgress for entering in drunk. The understanding
was that these things would make you drunk and they were included
in when it says יין ושכר אל תשת, yayin ve-shichar al tesht,
don't drink wine and שכר, shichar, that שכר shichar would be anything
that made you intoxicated. So maybe שכר shichar is not limited to
type of a beer or mead that makes you drunk, maybe there's
foods that make you drunk. And maybe it's still that's why it's
called אכילה achilah and it's and אכילה, achilah, the word, that verb
does not apply to drinks. אלא Ela fine, יליף שכר שכר מנזיר.
yalif shichar shichar minazir.
I'll tell you how we know שכר shichar in that verse where
it says don't eat means real beer or mead because that's what
it means by נזיר. Nazir. מה להלן יין אף כאן יין. Ma
lehal yayin, af kan yayin.
Because there by the נזיר, Nazir, right, it says, it says, right,
שכר, shichar, no, כל משרת ענבים לא ישתה, kol mishrat anavim lo
yishteh, כל אשר יצא מגפן היין מחרצנים ועד זג לא
יאכל.
kol asher yetze migeven hayayin mechartzanim
v'ad zag lo yochel.
No, there's somewhere it says יין ושכר. yayin v'shichar. There's רש"י Rashi
quoted it.
I don't I can't remember the פסוק pasuk off the top of
my head. If Micha was here he would look it up. Anyway,
by the נזיר Nazir it mentions that the נזיר Nazir should not
drink יין yayin or שכר. shichar. Okay, so there clearly שכר shichar
it's used with the verb drink. So it means something you drink.
And therefore and there the juxtaposition of שכר shichar and יין. yayin.
יין yayin is in its natural form, and you're drinking it, it's
not in some type of a food. So מה להלן ma lahalan
יין yayin the same way the שכר sheichar by the נזיר Nazir
means is wine or is connected to wine, אף כאן af kan
יין yayin here too when it says, you know, when it says
ביין ושכר יזיר. beyayin vesheichar yazir. Thank you very much. So anyway
so here too when it says ביין ובשכר, beyayin uvesheichar,
so it means in its liquid form and it means actual actual
drinking wine and nevertheless it refers to it as eating. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ותירוש חמרא הוא? vetirosh chamra hu?
You really mean to tell me תירוש tirosh means wine? Because again
we now are asserting that the verse that says right, what was
the verse, מעשר דגנך תירושך ויצהרך? ma'asar degancha tiroshcha veyitzharecha? That תירוש
tirosh means wine, and as we've now asserted it means wine in
its sort of liquid form, you know as a drink. But is
this really true? Your assumption that תירוש tirosh means
wine? דתניא, detanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braita, הנודר מן התירוש hanoder min hatirosh אסור בכל מיני
מתיקה. assur bechol minei metika. Somebody takes a vow against eating תירוש,
tirosh, that refers to any sweet things, meaning like sweet fruits, ומותר
ביין, umutar beyayin, but you can drink wine. So clearly תירוש tirosh
does not mean wine, תירוש tirosh means like sweet, you know sweet
fruits. So הגמרא haGemara says ולאו חמרא הוא? velav chamra hu? What,
you think תירוש tirosh doesn't mean wine? והכתיב vehachtiv the verse says
ותירוש ינובב בתולות, vetirosh yenovev betultot, the wine will sort of flow
forth from virgins. Now what does that mean? Does it mean the
virgin soil? Does it mean רש"י Rashi says it means that it
will sort of like cause you to like you know cause secrets
to come out, cause you know things that are like private and
closed to flow forth? But anyway it seems that we're talking not
about fruit but about wine and the power of wine. So no,
דבר הבא מן התירוש. davar haba min hatirosh.
תירוש tirosh literally we're asserting doesn't mean wine, it means sweet fruit,
but this verse it means things that come from the sweet fruit.
So it means wine derivatively, but primarily it means sweet fruit. Here
it means things that come from it.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute. דבר הבא מן התירוש
ינובב בתולות. davar haba min hatirosh yenovev betultot. והכתיב vehachtiv but the
verse says ותירוש יקביך יפריצו, vetirosh yikavecha yafritzu, the תירוש tirosh of
your wine presses will burst forth. So clearly תירוש tirosh means wine.
A יקב yekev is a wine press, a wine vat I should
say. דבר הבא מן התירוש. davar haba min hatirosh. No, תירוש tirosh
itself means the fruit, here it means the stuff that comes out
of the תירוש. tirosh. Again, if it means תירוש tirosh means the
stuff that comes out of the תירוש, tirosh, at the end of
the day it's going to mean
wine anyway. Okay, יקביך יפריצו, yikavecha yafritzu, that will cause your wine
vats to burst forth. והכתיב vehachtiv but the verse says וזנות ויין
ותירוש יקח לב, veznut veyayin vetirosh yikach lev, fornication wine and תירוש
tirosh will take away the heart, will like lead you astray. אלא
דכולי עלמא תירוש חמרא הוא. ela dechulei alma tirosh chamra hu. Fine,
you're right, תירוש tirosh means wine. Now again I don't know why
this verse more than anything else persuaded them, say here תירוש tirosh
means something that comes from תירוש. tirosh. Anyway finally it admits, it
concedes that תירוש tirosh means wine. So what about this idea of
taking the vow? ובנדרים הלך אחר לשון בני אדם. uvenedarim halech achar
leshon benei adam. Fine, people nowadays if you want to say wine
you say יין, yayin, and if you say תירוש tirosh you mean
you mean sweet fruit. In the time of the תורה Torah though,
תירוש tirosh had the biblical sense, that means wine. I concede the
point. Okay, ואמאי קרי ליה יין? ve'amai kari leh yayin? Now that
we're talking about the words that are used to describe wine, so
we're going to talk about that for a bit. Why is it
called יין? yayin? ואמאי קרי ליה תירוש? ve'amai kari leh tirosh? What
does the word signify if it has two words, if תירוש tirosh
in the biblical sense means wine, only later it got a different
meaning, why are there two biblical terms for it? What does each
one mean? So יין שמביא יללה לעולם. yayin shemevi yilala la'olam. So
now again we're going back to the power of food and perhaps
the things you have to be, now it's more of I think
a clearly sort of religious message, you know more of the things
that you have to be aware of when you're engaging in consumption.
So wine can bring can bring moaning to the world, wailing. It
can lead people to go astray and to do terrible things and
so on. So רש"י Rashi says the idea of יללה yilala is
because it's תאניה. ta'aniya.
You know the word תאניה ta'aniya means like moaning.
So that's a statement that identifies the עץ הדעת etz hadaat in
גן עדן gan eden as being גפן. gefen.
That's a good point too, that it's גפן gefen שמביא יללה
לעולם.
shemevi
yilala la'olam.
That's a good point, right, and that that's a good point that
it could connect to that idea of at the first you know
thing that אדם הראשון, Adam HaRishon, certainly by נח Noach you get
the wine, you know already early in the stage of world history.
תירוש, tirosh, how about תירוש? tirosh? שכל המתגרה בו נעשה רש. shechol
hamitgareh bo na'aseh rash. Same type of message. Anybody that is like
you know competes with this, or meaning you know indulges himself with
it will become poor. You know you'll feed your habit, you'll lose
your job. So again, some of the word רש. rash. Okay, so
the מתגרה mitgareh is probably the ת tav and the ר resh
out of it or whatever I don't know. Anyway, רב כהנא רמי.
Rav Kahana rami. כתיב תירש, ketiv tirash, תירוש tirosh וקרינן תירוש vekarinan
tirosh or
תירש. tirash. It's written without the ו. vav, I don't know where
it's written without the ו, and we read it תירוש, tirosh, so
you have the רש rash and the ראש. rosh. זכה נעשה ראש.
zacha na'aseh rosh. If you're able to drink your wine in moderation,
please drink responsibly, then you can become a head. Then it's good,
it
helps. socialize and maybe it even puts you in a better frame
of mind if you can be responsible about it it's good לא
זכה lo zacha if you're not merit you're not responsible נעשה רש
na'aseh rash it'll impoverish you okay so it's not all
bad okay there's wine in moderation can be good והיינו דרבא ve-hainu
de-Rava that's what Rava דרבא רמי כתיב de-Rava rami ktiv one verse
says ישמח yesomach wine will bring joy to לבב אנוש levav enosh
יין ישמח לבב אנוש yayin yesamach levav enosh
וקרינן ve-karinan ישמח yeshamach and you could read it with a shin
okay what does that mean זכה משמחו zacha mesamcho if you merit
if you do it in moderation and properly it'll bring joy לא
זכה משממו lo zacha meshamemo so like ישמח yeshamach or ישממו yeshamemo
it'll lead to שממון shimamon it'll lead to desolation and destruction והיינו
דאמר רבא ve-hainu de-amar Rava and that's what Rava says
חמרא וריחני פקחין chamra ve-reichani pikchin wine and aromatic spices fragrances have
made me smart like they were good they put me in a
good frame of mind and they helped me they actually helped my
studies and helped me in my sort of have a clear mind
okay so that's the end of that little thing so this is
actually quite fascinating this actually is more of a whole discussion about
food and moral or religious responsibility around food that sometimes could be
a double-edged sword it could be a very positive but you can
overindulge and it could lead to very negatives particularly something like wine
it has which is intoxicating and can be addictive and so on
looks like you want to say
something yeah well it's interesting that they use the word זכה zacha
לא זכה lo zacha right which typically refers to being worthy or
deserving aha oh
that's interesting right because זכה zacha means like would more suggest like
something not either because of your deeds because you're a צדיק tzaddik
or a רשע rasha so or but certainly not something that's about
sort of your choice and what I translated it as if you
do it in moderation so that's interesting so not
everybody who overindulges in wine is an alcoholic
right exactly and not everybody that's born with addictive tendencies becomes alcoholic
either but you're right there's an element of a זכה zacha and
לא זכה lo zacha there in terms of a predisposition that's a
very good point okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this
fine so we said that was a little interesting connected digression but
we're now said that אכילה ושתיה achila ve-shtiya in our list we
have this idea of חמישה עינויים chamisha inuyim we're counting אכילה ושתיה
achila ve-shtiya as one it's one plus four ואכילה ושתיה ve-achila ve-shtiya
we know that's biblical that's כרת karet and so on plus an
extra four okay and we're counting אכילה ושתיה achila ve-shtiya as one
so they are one sort of unified category although halachically as I
said eating and drinking don't combine now I want to alert you
to something which maybe I'll make a mention because I won't be
here tomorrow that it learned it all from a פסוק Pasuk it's
learning it like it's a real דרשה drasha and like it's a
real דאורייתא de-oraita and this is going to be the question whether
the עינויים inuyim are biblical or
rabbinic okay what does if אכילה ושתיה achila ve-shtiya is the one
where we're saying that's the verse that if you transgress the law
you get כרת karet that's what the פסוקים psukim are talking about
but through these multiple times it says it we include other things
is that also biblical but of a different level or is that
just אסמכתא asmachta so keep that in mind let's read a little
bit more so the גמרא Gemara says like this רחיצה וסיכה מנלן
דאיקרי עינוי rechitza ve-sicha minalan de-ikri inuy if you want to include
bathing and anointing in the verse of תענו te-anu afflicting where do
you get that these things are called affliction not doing them דכתיב
de-chtiv the verse says like by Daniel לחם חמודות לא אכלתי lechem
chamudot lo achalti I did not eat bread of desire ובשר ויין
לא בא אל פי u-vasar ve-yayin lo ba el pi and no
wine and meat came into my mouth meaning he wasn't fasting but
he was being abstaining from indulgence וסוך לא סכתי ve-soch lo sachti
and I did not anoint myself so מאי לחם חמודות לא אכלתי
mai lechem chamudot lo achalti what does it mean bread of desire
I did not eat אמר רב יהודה בריה דרב שמואל בר שילת
amar Rav Yehuda brei de-Rav Shmuel bar Shilat אפילו נהמא דחיטי דקיותא
afilu nahama de-chiti dakyasa even bread of like clean
wheat of fine wheat לא אכל lo achal I didn't eat meaning
not only like I didn't eat stuff like with butter and made
up and all things even just like clean white bread I didn't
eat I was very much on a subsistence
style okay ומנלן דחשיב כעינוי u-minalan de-chashiv ke-inuy fine that was a
digression now how do you know that this fact that he withheld
himself from these things is described as עינוי inuy and including the
anointing דכתיב de-chtiv because the verse says ויאמר אלי אל תירא דניאל
va-yomer elai al tira Daniel and he said to me do not
fear Daniel כי מן היום אשר נתת את לבך להבין ולהתענות לפני
אלהיך ki min hayom asher natata et libcha le-havin u-le-hitanot lifnei Elohecha
from the day that you have given your heart to understand and
to להתענות le-hitanot to fast or to afflict yourself before your God
נשמעו דבריך nishme'u devarecha your words have been heard ואני באתי בדבריך
ve-ani bati bi-devarecha and I came as a result of your words
this was the vision that happened to that occurred to Daniel afterwards
so he describes what happened as להתענות le-hitanot okay now maybe the
להתענות le-hitanot was because he didn't eat the bread or the or
have the meat and the wine but presumably no that's not enough
for עינוי inuy for עינוי inuy regarding food you have to completely
abstain so להתענות le-hitanot is referring to either the totality of it
which part of it is the not anointing Or maybe even specifically
to the anointing, and that's how we know that abstaining from anointing
is a type of עינוי. Inui. By the way, I think it's
hard for us to always understand what's this big deal with anointing.
I mean who has, who like you know, but first of all,
we do have all of these things, all these lotions that we
put on, which is essentially our modern version, that was the point
of keeping the moisture and keeping the skin moisturized. So that's number
one. And number two is, I think I read but I might
be misremembering, you know, if you have a because I don't know
if this because I think they did a lot of oil stuff
in Roman times as well.
Exactly the way they used, instead of soap, they would put oil
and then they would scrape it all. There was an implement. If
you go into the מרחצאות Mirchatzaot that archaeologists have reconstructed, they actually
have found these implements. They would put oil, hot oil on their
body and that would like loosen up the dirt
and they would scrape it off.
Somebody scraped it off.
Right, so thank you.
Right, so I think that's the סיכה. Sicha.
So that's, so thank you. It is also just for moisturizing purposes,
but yes it is very much connected to cleansing and רחיצה. Rechitza.
Right, like using soap, right, using, right.
Okay.
In some places it's certainly true. Yeah.
In California they give you a free bottle of wine in the
room, so it's water you pay five bucks.
There you go. אשכחן סיכה, Ashkan sicha,
that's anointing. רחיצה מנלן, Rechitza minalan, how about bathing? אמר רב זוטרא
בריה דרב טוביה אמר קרא, Amar Rav Zutra brei d'Rav Tuvia amar
kra, the verse says: ותבוא כמים בקרבו וכשמן בעצמותיו. Vatavo chamayim b'kirbo
k'shemen b'atzmotav.
And it came like water into his, into
inside of him and like oil in his bones. So the same
way oil on your bones, you get oil by rubbing the oil
in, so presumably it's being compared to water that's being, you're bathing
yourself with water. Of course you could say it means drinking water,
which is what the גמרא Gemara is going to suggest, but at
this read it is the bathing with water is being parallel to
the rubbing of the oil into your skin.
How do you see the סיכה Sicha from the earlier פסוק from
Daniel?
It says וסוך לא סכתי. V'soch lo sachti. He says I did
not, I did not anoint myself, I did not rub, I did
not rub oil onto myself. That's in the verse. לחם חמודות לא
אכלתי ובשר ויין לא בא אל פי וסוך לא
סכתי.
Lechem chamudot lo achalti basar v'yayin lo va el pi v'soch
lo sachti.
Ah, understood. Okay.
ואימא כשתייה, V'eima k'shtiya,
maybe it means that the, maybe the מים בקרבו Mayim b'kirbo is
drinking. It's comparing putting oil on your skin to drinking water. No,
דומייא דשמן, Dumya d'shemen, it's comparable to the reality of the oil.
מה שמן מבחוץ, Ma shemen mibachutz, the same way the oil is
applied topically on the outside, אף מים מבחוץ, Af mayim mibachutz, we're
talking about water applied topically. So we're comparing the oil with the
bathing. And again, as Dove pointed out, it was made very much
a part of the bathing process. תניא איפכא? Tanya ipcha? Wait one
minute, we have a תנא Tanna who learns the verse the other
way, that learns that the מים בקרבו Mayim b'kirbo refers to drinking
and the point of the verse is to tell you an opposite
teacher, not opposite, but a different teacher. דתנן, Detnan, מנלן לסיכה כשתייה
ביום הכיפורים? Minalan l'sicha k'shtiya b'Yom HaKippurim?
As opposed to what we said that we located סיכה Sicha in
the verse by Daniel about fasting, here a ברייתא Braita says how
do you know סיכה's Sicha like drinking on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur?
Okay. אף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר. Af al pi
she'ein raya l'davar zecher l'davar. Although there's no proof, there's a hint.
שנאמר, ותבוא כמים בקרבו וכשמן בעצמותיו. Vatavo chamayim b'kirbo k'shemen b'atzmotav.
It's like water inside of you and oil in your bones. So
rather than telling you that water bathing is like rubbing oil in,
it's just the opposite. Rubbing oil in your skin is like drinking,
and it's comparing oil to drinking. So the same way you can't
drink, you can't rub oil in your skin and that's the source.
So that's another source for סיכה. Sicha. But now we don't know
how you know רחיצה. Rechitza. אלא אמר רב אשי, Ela amar Rav
Ashi, רחיצה מגופיה דקרא שמיע ליה. Rechitza migufa d'krah shamia lei. You
can infer it from the verse. דכתיב, Dechtiv, וסוך לא סכתי, V'soch
lo sachti, and I did not anoint myself, meaning the double language,
he doesn't just say ולא סכתי. V'lo sachti. The double language includes
things that are all part of that whole process. So as again
we just said, the oil rubbing it in is part of the
bathing and cleansing process and the double language includes bathing. Now, I'm
going to stop here and say two things before we finish because
I want to use the extra one minute or two minutes to
say something which is: number one, so saying that anointing is like
drinking, again, makes the anointing much more serious, it's not just an
additional עינוי, Inui, it's a quasi-drinking, it's a way of getting liquids
into your body and topically you're drinking it, which would put a
lot of weight on the problem of the oil, maybe even more
than the other עינויים. Inuim. It certainly could suggest the idea that
this is דאורייתא, D'oraita, included in the she and so on. So
this is a major debate of the ראשונים. Rishonim. Some ראשונים Rishonim
say yes it's דאורייתא, D'oraita, not so much because of סיכה כשתייה,
Sicha k'shtiya, there's a whole discussion when do we say סיכה כשתייה.
Sicha k'shtiya. I mean normally if like you're not allowed to drink,
a נזיר Nazir can't drink wine. If he rubs wine on his
skin, he hasn't transgressed. You know, you're not allowed to drink I
don't know חלב, Chelev, if you rub חלב Chelev on your skin
you haven't transgressed. Basically we don't say סיכה כשתייה. Sicha k'shtiya. We
only say סיכה כשתייה Sicha k'shtiya when there's a problem of deriving
benefit, or there's a problem of עינוי, Inui, of trying to afflict
yourself, then we have broader definitions. So number one is, סיכה כשתייה
Sicha k'shtiya is a much more
limited... Given all this discussion סיכה כשתייה, sicha k'shiya, the verse and
עינוי עינוי עינוי, inuy inuy inuy, is it דאורייתא de'oraisa or is
it not? is a major debate of ראשונים. rishonim. Some say it
is, פסוקים סתם ומר pesukim stam u'mar sounds, take it seriously. Others
say no, the very fact that we could say for example a
king could wash his face, a כלה kallah could wash her face,
if you've got some scabs on you could put oil on, whatever,
that we give allowances, shows that it's all דרבנן. derabbanan. Others respond
back and say no no no, you know, maybe the תורה Torah
gave a lot of latitude to the rabbis to define the parameters,
but at the end of the day, עינוי inuy is a very
abstract word, so the rabbis could define the parameters, but at the
end of the day, whatever parameters the rabbis defined, that is included,
that's part of a biblical fulfillment of or mandate of this idea
of עינוי. inuy. So there is this very fascinating debate which we're
beginning to see, you know, where the idea could come that it's
דאורייתא. de'oraisa. I'll read you one line in the next תוספות Tosafot
on ע''ז ע''א ayin zayin amud aleph which I'm allowed to read
because it's on the previous דף, daf, if you see מניין לסיכה
כשתייה. minayin l'sicha k'shiya. So if you look in the middle of
that תוספות, Tosafot, he says,
the line starts with אוכל טבל בדמיסה, ochel tevel b'dimisa, like you
see where the line has a ג ע''ב gimel amud beis and
a half of a parenthesis there in this תוספות Tosafot about fifteen
lines down, the line begins with like a ג ע''ב, gimel amud
beis, right? So go two lines below, three lines below, two lines,
three lines below that, he says, ופירש רבנו תם דכל עינויים דיום
הכיפורים, u'peirash Rabbeinu Tam d'chol inuyim d'Yom HaKippurim, the line starts with
the word יום הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim, לאו נינהו אלא מדרבנן, lav ninhu
ela miderabbanan, they're just rabbinic, דקרא אסמכתא בעלמא, d'kra asmachta b'alma,
and the verse is an אסמכתא asmachta בעלמא, b'alma, לבר מאכילה ושתייה,
l'bar me'achilah u'shtiyah, obviously except for eating and drinking. How do you
know it? דאמר לקמן, d'amar l'kaman, ואם היה מלוכלך בטיט ובצואה, v'im
hayah meluchlach b'tit u'v'tzoah, if you were dirty with like, you know,
dung or whatever, רוחץ כדרכו ואינו חושש, rochetz k'darko v'eino choshesh, you're
allowed to clean it off. מי שיש לו חטטים בראשו, mi sheyesh
lo chatatim b'rosho, if you have scabs on your head, סך כדרכו
ואינו חושש, sach k'darko v'eino choshesh, you get it off with some
oil. So how could we allow it if it was biblical? So
therefore he says it must be it's all דרבנן. derabbanan. This is
one approach. The other approach, as I said, says no, it's biblical,
but the rabbis have some latitude to define what are its parameters.
By the way, and this is the last thing, point I'll make,
regarding this issue, you don't even have to say it's an exception.
You could say the type, and this is an important question to
be thinking of as we continue, it's not that רחיצה rechitza is
absolutely forbidden. It's רחיצה rechitza that is that is categorized as a
type of a pleasurable רחיצה, rechitza, סיכה sikha that is seen as
pleasurable. If you're doing a רחיצה rechitza to get away dirt or
you're doing a סיכה sikha to get away something, you know, for
more, you know, for medicinal purposes or to remove some something, that's
not תענוג, ta'anug, that's not pleasure, right? That's doing some other purpose.
So there is a way to explain some of this, that it
is biblical, and even without saying the rabbis are allowed to make
exceptions within the parameters of the biblical, it's more definitional. What type
of רחיצה rechitza is forbidden? What type of סיכה sikha is forbidden?
Maybe only a רחיצה rechitza and a סיכה sikha that brings pleasure,
not a רחיצה rechitza and a סיכה sikha that gets rid of
dirt or that gets rid of some irritant. Okay, so that is
a very important question to be thinking of when we deal with
the exceptions about, a, do we frame it as an exception or
definitional, and, b, this question of biblical or rabbinic.
So you have some of the relevance of.